Guide to the Committees of Correspondence (U.S) Records TAM.220
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Committees of Correspondence (U.S.) Records
1991-1997, 2007-ongoing
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Committees of Correspondence (U.S.)
TAM.220
1.5 Linear Feet in one record carton and two manuscript boxes.
6 websites in 6 archived websites.
The Committees on Correspondence was organized in 1992 after the 1991 Communist Party USA convention as a non-Leninist, democratic socialist organization to dispute the policies and leadership of CPUSA head, Gus Hall. The movement centered around the respected veteran communist and former leading CP official, Gil Green (1906-1997). Around 2000, the Committee on Correspondence changed its name to the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism. The collection includes: letters, memos, statements, minutes, photographs, archived websites, and emails that document formation of the organization and national leadership meeting minutes.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by the Committees of Correspondence in circa 2000. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2000.010, 2000.011, and NPA.2005.071.
https://www.cc-ds.org/ was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Communism, Socialism, Trotskyism Web Archive. http://www.ccds-discussion.org/ and http://www.ncalccds.org/ were added in 2009 and 2010, respectively. In November 2015, these websites were migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In 2025, https://www.cc-ds.org/publications/ccdslinks-4/ and https://archive.constantcontact.com/fs082/1103584185760/archive/1103630604546.html were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2025.020.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Historical Note
The Committees on Correspondence was organized in 1992 after the 1991 Communist Party USA convention as a non-Leninist, democratic socialist organization to dispute the policies and leadership of then CPUSA head, Gus Hall. The movement centered around the Communist and former leading CPUSA official, Gil Green (1906-1997). The Committees on Correspondence sought to reach out to others on the left outside of the CPUSA, and held conferences in 1992 and 1994 to formally establish the new organization. Around 2000, the Committee on Correspondence changed its name to the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism.
Related Materials
Gil Green Papers (TAM 095)
Scope and Content Note
The content of this collection reflects the origins of the Committees of Correspondence. Since the split with the CPUSA was in large measure connected to different approaches towards democratic processes within the Party, these procedures make up much of the discussions found in the collection. There is also discussion of the meaning and relevance of socialism and socialist ideas in light of the collapse of the Communist bloc. Discussions of the envisioned character of the new organization are in various forms: letters, memos, statements, executive committee and national coordinating committee meeting minutes, photographs of members, and emails. The national leadership discussions are documented in detailed minutes and handwritten notes by participants; the same is true for the national conventions. Although the Committees of Correspondence consisted of many local branches, it is only the Northern Californians whose activities are reflected here. The correspondence is largely national with contacts to the international leftist scene. The archived websites contain convention materials, editorials by membership, publications, a discussion board, and the Northern California chapter website.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Socialism -- United States.; Correspondence.; Electronic mail.; Communism -- United States.; Minutes (administrative records); Committees of Correspondence (U.S.); Green, Gil, 1906-; Communist Party of the United States of America; Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism
- Photographs, 1991-1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Cleveland Meeting of the Initiative, Nov 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- From "Initiative" to Committees of Correspondence, Nov 1991-Jan 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Initiative, Oct 1991-Dec 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters in Response to the Appeal of the "Ad Hoc Committee", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Notes on the Cleveland-Convention by a Dissident, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "People's Weekly World" Lockout, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Post-Cleveland Position Papers of Committees of Correspondence Members, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Statements Concerning the Split, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Financial Records, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Committees of Correspondence-Youth Caucus, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence with Japanese Activist, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- National Coordinating Committee Minutes, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- National Executive Committee Minutes, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- New York Committees of Correspondence - Meeting, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- San Francisco Conference - Endorsements, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- San Francisco Conference - Reactions and Statements, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- San Francisco Conference - Speeches, Resolutions, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- San Francisco Conference - Workshops, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence with German Activists, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Kendra Alexander (1946-1993), 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Committees of Correspondence - Regional Initiatives (California), 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Correspondence with South African Activists, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Committees of Correspondence Flyers, Invites, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Press Releases, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Committees of Correspondence Videos, 1992-1996 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- National Coordinating Committee Minutes, Jun 1993 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- National Executive Committee Minutes, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Proposals for Structures and Goals of the Committees of Correspondence, circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Correspondence with French Activists, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Founding Convention Preparation - Delegates, Committees, Tables, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Rules Committee for the Founding Convention, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- By Laws Committee, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Co-Chairs, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Convention Advertisement Journals, 1994, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Convention Greetings, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Correspondence: Post-Convention Thank You Notes, Jul 1994-Aug 1994 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Founding Convention - Speaker Invitations, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Founding Convention - Speeches, Statements, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Name Proposals, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- National Coordinating Committee Minutes, Jan 1994 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- National Coordinating Committee Minutes, Nov 1994 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- National Executive Committee Minutes, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Nominations - Convention (with biographies), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Programmatic Suggestions for Committees of Correspondence and Founding Convention, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Correspondence, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- National Coordinating Committee Minutes, May 1995 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- National Coordinating Committee Convention, Dec 1995 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- South Africa Trip, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Co-Chairs, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Committees of Correspondence Convention - By Laws, Resolutions, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Convention Arrangements (Invites, Registrations), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Committees of Correspondence Convention - Comments (Post Convention), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Convention - Cultural Event, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Convention - Memos, Drafts, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Convention - Nominations and Elections, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Convention Preparations: Workshops, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- National Coordinating Committee Minutes, Mar 1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- National Coordinating Committee Minutes, Dec 1996 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- National Executive Committee Minutes, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- National Executive Committee Minutes, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Archived Websites, October 2007-ongoing
  Scope and Content Note
  Capture of the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism's web presence began in 2007. The website contained their publications Dialogue and Initiative, the Mobilizer, and the Corresponder, dating back to 1997. The website also includes CCDS statements on American politics dating back to 2000, as well as information on their Socialist Eduation Project. In 2009, the CCDS Discussion website was created for their biennial convention. The discussion website contains opinion pieces and comments by the membership on topics such as race, climate change, elections, healthcare, energy, labor, left unity, militarism, Marxism, neoliberalism, police repression, world politics, Wall Street, political economy, and social economy. In 2013, the main website for CCDS redesigned and added obituaries of members and convention materials, including tools for young activists to build solidarity. The website redesigned again in 2014, 2018, and 2021. Their newsletter, LeftLinks, is predominately written and edited by Carl Davidson. The web presence also includes the website for the Northern California chapter of the organization, dating from 2009-2022.
  Accruals
  http://www.cc-ds.org/ is accrued semmiannually. LeftLinks is accrued weekly.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.